Guide to the Centro de Accion Social Autonomo Papers, 1963-1978
Department of Special Collections
Centro de Accion Social Autonomo Papers,
1963-1978
Special Collections M0325
Centro de Accion Social Autonomo
27.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions:
None.
Provenance:
Gift of Bert Corona and Antonio Rodriguez, 1980.
ABSTRACT
The CASA collection consists of correspondence, reports, minutes, agendas, notes, press releases, audiotapes, photographs and ephemera documenting the history of CASA, a grass roots social and legal services agency and Marxist-Leninist political organization.
BIOGRAPHY
Founded in Los Angeles in 1968, the Centro de Accion Social Autonomo-Hermandad General de Trabajadores (Center for Autonomous Social Action-General Brotherhood of Workers or simply, CASA) operated for ten years as a vocal and active political group within the Mexican American community. Though short-lived, the organization nonetheless occupied an influential position in a portion of that community, and, in many ways, reflected the growth and development of a distinct Mexican American political consciousness during the 1960s and 1970s. The organization's problems, ranging from internal factionalization and ideological dispute to external repression and financial difficulties, likewise mirrored the obstacles faced by many activist organizations of the era.
Background
Like other ethnic groups, Mexican Americans experienced a resurgence of cultural identity and political autonomy during the 1960s. Influenced by a renewed sense of their own history, turbulent events in the United States, and a powerful student movement in Mexico, Mexican Americans began to reassess their position in American society. Collectively concerned with their depressed status, they organized around such issues as land and labor reform, civil rights, education, and political participation. Together, the increasing political expression and ethnic pride of the Mexican American people helped constitute the "Chicano Movement."
The founding of CASA took place in the midst of this movement. However, CASA differed from most other contemporary Chicano groups in that it was designed as a distinctively working-class organization aimed at providing aid to the Mexican workingman and woman in the United States. Specifically, CASA committed itself to assist the undocumented Mexican laborer. Coming at a time when concern for indocumentados was weak, CASA's commitment was its most distinguishing feature.
In founding CASA in 1968, Bert Corona and Soledad "Chole" Alatorre utilized their experience as longtime organizers of Mexican American labor. Alatorre had been a union organizer for years, and Corona was affiliated with the International Longshoreman's and Warehouseman's Union as well as a founding member and former president of the Mexican American Political Association (MAPA). These two individuals formed CASA (or CASA-MAPA as it was first known) as a local, urban mutual aid organization not unlike the traditional Mexican form of community welfare, the mutualists.
Early Years
CASA's early activities centered around a grass roots program of helping and educating the Mexican worker in the United States. By the early 1970s, independent affiliate CASA groups had been formed in other California cities, in Chicago, and throughout the Southwest. Decision-making and planning radiated down from the Political Commission, a national body of elected members, through the local committees to the largely volunteer rank and file members that constituted the nucleii.* Estimates of membership are difficult to make, but one scholar estimates that by 1972, over 2,000 volunteers made up the nationwide core membership of CASA. Case files indicate that the Los Angeles office assisted some 6,000 indocumentados from 1969 to 1973; such assistance ranged from providing legal aid and counseling to sponsoring social functions.1
Beginning in 1973, the character and orientation of the organization underwent great change. CASA stepped out of the barrio to oppose proposed changes in federal immigration law and increased raids by the Immigration and Naturalization Service (INS). These programmatic changes led, in turn, to a shift in CASA membership. The expansion of the CASA agenda away from localized, working-class roots into wider political
* In July 1975, the National Coordinating Commission was added above the Political Commission to oversee national archives. confrontation attracted more ideologically radical members. Most new CASAmembers were associated with either the Los Angeles-based Casa Carnalismo (a militant group formed to fight drugs in the barrio) or the National Committee to Free Los Tres, a group formed in response to the arrest and conviction of three Casa Carnalismo members for the assault of a federal officer posing as a drug dealer in East Los Angeles.
The inclusion of these new members, many of whom espoused some sort of Marxist-Leninist doctrine, produced division factions within CASA. The "old guard" leadership of Bert Corona and Chole Alatorre maintained that CASA's primary responsibility was to assist unorganized and undocumented workers. Those associated with Casa Carnalismo or the National Committee sought to "deemphasize the social-service aspect of the organization, hoping to transform CASA into a `revolutionary vanguard' dedicated to the `liberation of the Mexican people.'"2 This factionalization culminated in the resignation of both Corona and Alatorre in late 1974.
A New CASA
The new CASA leadership, composed of young, well-educated Chicanos, turned the organization in a decidedly Marxist-Leninist direction. As Carlos Vasquez, a member of the CASA Political Commission and Commissioner of Information and Propaganda, wrote in 1976: We have gone from a defensive organization to an offensive and potentially clandestine organization prepared for a protracted struggle.3
As ideology shifted, CASA embraced a myriad of causes and issues. Members traveled to major socialist and radical conferences, study groups were formed to study revolutionary politics and tactics, and the group developed an effective voice in the newspaper Sin Fronteras. Originally the organ of the National Coalition for Fair Immigration Laws and Practices, Sin Fronteras was moved from the CASA office in San Antonio to Los Angeles in the mid-1970s. There, true to its name ("Without Borders"), the newspaper emphasized the solidarity of the Mexican proletariat on either side of the border.
CASA's ideological shifts were not without consequences. The energy of the organization was channeled in new directions. CASA spent time and money on campaigns fighting the deportation of Mexican attorney and activist José Jacques Medina, the University of California reverse discrimination (Bakke) decision, and new immigration restriction proposals. Membership and community support for the group fell as its local presence waned. Several local chapters withdrew from the national organization. The Federal Bureau of Investigation monitored the group quite closely, aided apparently by an internal informant.4
By far the most serious problem stemming from CASA's ideological swing was the increasing factionalization it caused. Externally, CASA came under attack by other Chicano groups for its seeming lack of commitment to Chicano solidarity. Internally, the leadership divided over similar lines. Was the organization to be one primarily concerned with race or class? Was CASA to speak for the workingman and woman in an international context or only to the Mexican laborer? One side favored the former, only to be accused of a lack of devotion to Aztlan, the mythical Chicano homeland of the Southwest. One side favored the latter, only to be accused of chauvinism and racism.
In the end, the fractures within the CASA leadership were enough to disintegrate the group. The membership was neither powerful nor numerous enough to reconstitute the organization following the resignation of the entire Political Commission in 1978.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
The records of the Centro de Acción Social Autónomo-Hermandad General de Trabajadores (CASA-HGT) document in large part the organization's ten-year transition from a service center designed to aid its members in obtaining legal aid and social services to a Marxist-Leninist political organization dedicated to organizing working-class people of Mexican origin and publishing its views in the bilingual newspaper, Sin Fronteras. Consisting primarily of the Los Angeles office records, the collection's subject strengths include: policy and decision-making processes within the CASA national leadership, the creation and dissemination of Sin Fronteras, the Federal Bureau of Investigation surveillance of CASA, immigration reform, the immigration case of Mexican attorney Jose Jacques Medina, Chicano activism in East Los Angeles schools, the narcotics case of Los Tres del Barrio, and domestic and international socialist movements. The collection also includes photographs and tape recordings of CASA activities and its members.
The collection (27.5 linear ft.) is divided into six series: CASA Administrative Records, Federal Bureau of Investigation Reports on CASA, Subject and Organizational Files, Photographs, Ephemera, and Sound Recordings. The series are described below. Types of records include: agendas, articles, correspondence, flyers, legal documents, minutes, newsclippings, newsletters, notes, press releases, reports and statements.
SERIES DESCRIPTION
- SERIES I: CASA ADMINISTRATIVE RECORDS, 1968 -1978
  The first series contains records from CASA's national leadership, from its commissions (major policy-making bodies) and from the local organizations. There are comparatively few records dating from the period 1968-1974, during which CASA founders Bert Corona and Soledad Alatorre built a large membership of undocumented workers who joined the organization to obtain help with their legal problems. The bulk of the records date from 1975-1978, when Antonio Rodriguez rose to prominence in CASA leadership and membership composition shifted to young, mostly UnitedStates-born Mexican Americans with a commitment to socialist theory and politics.
  Among the most interesting documents in Series I are a history of CASA written in 1978 when the organization had begun to crumble, the minutes of national meetings which show the increased decentralization and gradual disaffection of local organizations, the planning and evaluative documents of Sin Fronteras, and the papers of Antonio Rodriguez.
- SERIES II: FEDEREAL BUREAU OF INVESTIGATION REPORTS ON CASA, 1972 -1978
  Through the Freedom of Information Act CASA members obtained copies of documents resulting from the FBI's surveillance of CASA. The FBI memoranda and reports date from April, 1972 to February, 1977. Both local CASA chapters and the national organization were being watched closely, presumably because of their advocacy of Marxist thought and their outspoken support for undocumented workers and for the Los Tres del Barrio defendants.
- SERIES III: SUBJECT AND ORGANIZATIONAL FILES, 1963 -1979
  The third series is further divided into seven sub-series: Chicano Movement, Education and Chicano Student Activism, Immigration Reform, Los Tres del Barrio Narcotics Case, Protest and Political Movements (United States), Protest and Political Movements (International), and Socialist Political Theory. It seems likely that at least some of these files were maintained by the Sin Fronteras staff as reference files to be used by the newspaper's writers. Representative topics within the Chicano Movement sub-series include the August 29th Movement, a rival Marxist-Leninist organization with which CASA was at ideological odds; La Raza Unida Party; and such issues as the Coors Beer Boycott and the police slaying of Los Angeles Times reporter Rubén Salazar, killed while covering the Chicano Moratorium Day riots in East Los Angeles in August, 1970.
  The major issues in the second sub-series, Education and Chicano Student Activism, include the Alan Bakke reverse discrimination decision for admission to the University of California and the events andconditions which led to the Chicano student walk-outs ("blowouts") at Los Angeles high schools in the late 1960s and early 1970s. This sub-series also contains the papers of Jorge Rodriguez, Antonio Rodriguez's younger brother, who led several student strikes and attempted to coordinate other protest activities at high schools and East Los Angeles Community College.
  The Immigration Reform Sub-series contains both CASA-generated records and records from organizations in which CASA participated, as well as reference files and information on the deportation case of Mexican lawyer José Jacques Medina. Although by 1975 CASA was spending less time helping individuals with their immigration problems, it had formed coalitions with other organizations, notably the National Coalition for Fair Laws and Practices, to keep immigration reform in the public eye. CASA organized and took part in rallies, marches, press conferences and campaigns designed to convince its members and others that the United States and its Latin American neighbors should enact legislation making them `sin fronteras' (without borders). Another major effort was support for the political asylum request of Medina, who was fighting deportation to Mexico for fear of reprisals for his participation in demonstrations at the Universidad Nacional Autónomo de México in 1973.
  Another case in which CASA was actively involved was that of Los Tres del Barrio. The papers concerning Los Tres form the next sub-series. The three men --Juan Ramón Fernandez, Alberto Ortiz Sanchez and Rodolfo Peña Sanchez --were convicted of narcotics charges while serving as drug counselors in East Los Angeles. Antonio Rodriguez served as legal counsel, and Sin Fronteras waged a campaign to have their sentences overturned.
  The next two sub-series deal with a wide range of domestic and international protest and political movements. These include anti-Vietnam War activities, Native American activism, industrial and farm labor union strikes in the United States, as well as socialist movements in Cuba, Mexico, and particularly Puerto Rico.
  The Socialist Political Theory Sub-series consists entirely of reprints of articles used by CASA members in their study groups and by Sin Fronteras writers as background for political articles.
- SERIES IV: PHOTOGRAPHS, 1973 -1977 AND n.d.
  This series contains photographs arranged by subject, most of which were assembled for use in Sin Fronteras. The range of subject matter is impressive and includes both newsworthy individuals (Jose Jacques Medina, Los Tres del Barrio, and Antonio Rodriguez) and events (demonstrations, strikes, and meetings). There are also twenty oversized matted photographs, which were apparently used for display
- SERIES V: EPHEMERA, n.d.
  This brief series consists primarily of miscellaneous items which were used to advertise CASA demonstrations and other activities, such as buttons, posters, original graphics, and a banner.
- SERIES VI: SOUND RECORDINGS, n.d.
  This series is made up of thirty-seven cassette tapes and two videocassettes. Many of the tapes are not identified as to event, speakers or date, and the sound quality is uneven. The tapes, in English, Spanish or a mixture of both languages, are apparently recordings of CASA meetings, press conferences and panel discussions.
- Series VII. Oversized Materials (Posters)
CONTAINER LIST
- SERIES I: CASA ADMINISTRATIVE RECORDS, 1968 -1978
  - Subseries A. General
    - Articles of incorporation and bylaws, 1969, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Boletin Interno, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Centro Legal, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, general, 1972-1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - History of CASA, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - National meeting, Nov. 28-30, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - National meeting, Dec. 21-22, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - National meeting, Apr. 8, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - National meeting, May 10-11, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - National meeting, committee reports July 5, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - National meeting, committee reports July 5, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - National meeting, manuscript notes and minutes July 5, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - National meeting, typed minutes July 5, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - National meeting,, Apr. 15-19, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - National meeting, July 1-4, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - National meeting, Dec. 17-18, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - National meeting, Feb. 1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - National meeting, May 21, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - National meeting, Oct. 7-8, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - National meeting, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - National meeting, National Investigatory Committee, Dec. 1977-Jan. 1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - National meeting, National Investigatory Committee, Feb. 1978 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - National membership regulations, description of CASA programs, ca. 1976 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Notes, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Notes, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Notes, Jan.-June, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Notes, July-Dec. 1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Notes, Jan.-Mar. 1976 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Notes, Apr.-June 1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Notes, July-Dec. 1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Notes, Jan.-July 1977 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Notes, Aug.-Dec. 1977 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Notes, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Notes, n.d. (1) (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Notes, n.d. (2) (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Notes, n.d. (3) (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Notes, n.d. (4) (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Notes, n.d. (5) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Notes, n.d. (6) (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Notes, n.d. (7) (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Notes, n.d. (8) (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Property deeds, 1972-1977 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Statements and reports, 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Statements and reports, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Statements and reports, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Statements and reports, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Statements and reports, n.d. (1) (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Statements and reports, n.d. (2) (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Statements and reports, n.d. (3) (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Statements and reports, n.d. (4) (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Statements and reports, n.d. (5) (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Statements and reports, "Jornada de Resistencia," n.d. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Subseries B. Bylaws and Resolutions Commissions
    - Bylaws and Resolutions Commissions 1976 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Subseries C. Finances Commission
    - Finances Commission, 1969-1973 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Finances Commission, 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Finances Commission, 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Finances Commission, Account books, bank book, 1975-1977 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Finances Commission, Correspondence, 1972-1977 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Finances Commission, Fund-raising, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Subseries D. Information and Propaganda Commission
    - Information and Propaganda Commission, 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Information and Propaganda Commission, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Information and Propaganda Commission, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Information and Propaganda Commission, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Information and Propaganda Commission, Flyers, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Information and Propaganda Commission, Pamphlets, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Organization Commission, Secretariat of Student Affairs, 1975-1977 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Subseries E. Political Commission
    - Political Commission, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Political Commission, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Political Commission, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Political Commission, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Political Commission, Report on World Trade Union Conference, Cyprus, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Political Commission, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Subseries F. Sin Fronteras Commission
    - Sin Fronteras Commission, Advertising, 1975-1978 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Sin Fronteras Commission, Bookstore proposal, 1976-1977 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, with Sin Fronteras correspondents, 1976-1977 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, with Pintos Unidos Mexicano Aztlan; "El Ruido," 1977 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Discussion documents for study group, 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Draft guide for production of paper, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Evaluation by Carlos Vasquez, 1976-1978 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Evaluation by Local Committees and Nucleos, 1974-1977 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Finances, dues, 1976-1978 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Finances, fund-raising, "Festival Sin Fronteras," 1976 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Finances, fund-raising, party, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Finances, fund-raising, ticket sales, 1976-1977 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Finances, reports, 1974-1978 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - La Raza Latin Press Association, 1976-1977 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - La Raza Latin Press Association, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Library, 1975-1977 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Minutes and agendas, 1975-1978 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - National campaign, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Notes and miscellany, 1976-1977 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Projections, 1976-1977 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Reports, 1975-1977 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Reports, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Distribution Sub-Committee, correspondence, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Distribution Sub-Committee, correspondence, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Distribution Sub-Committee, correspondence, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Distribution Sub-Committee, correspondence, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Distribution Sub-Committee, financial reports, 1975-1977 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Distribution Sub-Committee, mailing lists, 1975-1977 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Distribution Sub-Committee, other organizations, 1972-1976 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Distribution Sub-Committee, reports, 1975-July 1976 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Distribution Sub-Committee, Aug. 1976-1977 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Distribution Sub-Committee, sales reports, locals, Chicago, 1975-1977 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Distribution Sub-Committee, local sales reports, El Paso, 1976-1977 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Distribution Sub-Committee, local sales reports, Greeley, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Distribution Sub-Committee, local sales reports, Los Angeles, 1976-1977 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Distribution Sub-Committee, local sales reports, Los Angeles brigades and nucleos, A-J, 1975-1977 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Distribution Sub-Committee, local sales reports, L-R, 1975-1977 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Distribution Sub-Committee, local sales reports, New Mexico Chicano Center, 1975-1976 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Distribution Sub-Committee, local sales reports, Oakland, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Distribution Sub-Committee, local sales reports, Oakland, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Distribution Sub-Committee, local sales reports, San Antonio, 1975-1977 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Distribution Sub-Committee, local sales reports, San Jose, 1976-1978 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Distribution Sub-Committee, local sales reports, Santa Barbara, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Distribution Sub-Committee, local sales reports, Seattle, 1975-1976 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Production Subcommittee, notes by Lourdes Castaneda, 1974-1977 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Production Subcommittee, notes by Lourdes Castaneda ,n.d. (1) (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Production Subcommittee, notes by Lourdes Castaneda, n.d. (2) (Box 11, Folder 13)